A Guide to the Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, 1986-1989
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, 1986-1989
The Library of Virginia
33710
9 cu. ft.
Virginia. Office of the Secretary of Transportation
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was transferred by the Office of the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety, 18 January 1990.
Custodial History
This collection was transferred by the Secretary of Transportation and Public Saftey, but the collection has been filed under the Secretary of Transportation since the bulk of materials are relative to transportation.
Biographical Information
The Secretary of Transportation is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, they are selected by the governor, and subject to the approval of the General Assembly. The Secretary is responsible to the governor for the Department of Transportation, Department of Rail and Public Transportation, Department of Aviation, Department of Motor Vehicles, Virginia Port Authority and the Motor Vehicle Dealers Board. Their responsibilities include developing and implementing Virginia's transportation programs, including policies, financial oversight for six agencies and major projects.
The Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was responsible for the following departments: Dept. of Transportation, Dept. of Aviation, Dept. of Motor Vehicles, Dept. of Emergency Services, Dept. of Fire Programs, Dept. of Military Affairs, Dept. of Alcoholic Beverage Control, Dept. of Correctional Education, Dept. of Corrections, Dept. of Youth Services, Dept. of Criminal Justice Services, Dept. of State Police and the Virginia Parole Board.
In 1972, Governor Linwood Holton proposed to the General Assembly a restructuring of state agencies into six major departments each headed by a secretary to be appointed by the governor. On April 8, 1972 the Department of Transportation and Public Safety was created, by an act passed by the General Assembly. The Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations since its creation. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature established separate secretariats for transportation and for public safety, effective July 1, 1976. From July 1, 1984- 1990 the two entities would again be combined under one secretariat. On February 22, 1990 the two were again separated, and have remained so.
The individuals who served as Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety were: Wayne A. Whitham (1976-1978), George M. Walters (1978-1982), Andrew B. Forgarty (1982-1984), John G. Milliken (1990-1993), Robert Martinez (1994-1998), Shirley Ybarra (1998-2002), Whittington W. Clement (2002-2005), Pierce R. Homer (2005-2010), Sean T. Connaughton (2010-1012).
The individuals who served as Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety were: Wayne A. Whitham (1972-1976), Franklin E. White (1984-1985), Andrew B. Fogarty (1985-1986) and Vivian E. Watts (1986-1990).
The first Secretary of Transportation (and Public Safety) was, Wayne A. Whitham, a member of the Winchester City Council. Whitham was reappointed by Governor-elect Miles E. Godwin, Jr., in December 1973 and by Governor-elect John N. Dalton in December 1977. Whitham suffered a heart attack in August 1978 and resigned in December 1978. On June 7, 1984, Whitham died in Richmond, Virginia.
George M. Walters, a former top executive of the Reynolds Metals Corporation, to succeed Whitham as Secretary of Transportation. Walters served until the end of Dalton's term in January 1982. Governor-elect Charles S. Robb, the first Democrat to be elected governor since 1965, did not retain any of Dalton's cabinet secretaries. Robb appointed Andrew B. Fogarty, Dalton's assistant secretary for financial policy, as Secretary of Transportation.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of files about infrastructure developement, citizen complaints, and Dulles Airport. The bulk of this collection is correspondence from the Governor's Office, other correspondants include citizens concerned with transportation developments. There are also complaints from citizens about the practice of work release for inmates due to the fact that Mu'Min slipped away from her work to commited a murder, then just went back to jail, the problem being that inmates given work release were not being monitored properly. Types of documents included are letters, memorandums, and reports.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and Subjects Files, 1986-1989., Extent: 9 cu. ft. (9 boxes). (Box 1-9)
  This collection maintains the agency's original filing order, boxes 4-8 are arranged chronologically.
  - Manassas Battlefield, 1988. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Oil Overcharge, 1987. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Conrail, 1984-1986. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Route 17 - North Carolina, 1984. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Transportation Plan, 1981-1985. (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
  - National Governor's Association: Highway Transportation, 1986. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gasohol, 1979-1980. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Reciprocity Agreements, 1974-1984. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Special Funding, 1988-1989. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Legislation: Senate Joint Resolution 20, 1984. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Secretarial Reorganization: Critical Reevaluation, 1983. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Secretarial Reorganization Legislation, 1982. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Secretarial Reorganization Reports, 1983. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Department of Corrections: Budget Study, 1984. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Department of Corrections: Double Celling Inmates, 1986. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Department of Criminal Justice Services: Drug Prosecutions, 1986. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Department of Corrections: Interstate Compacts, 1987. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Department of Corrections: Prisoner Transportation, 1984-1985. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Department of Corrections: Study Bids, 1984. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Alcoholic Beverage Control: Drinking Ages, 1985. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Alcoholic Beverage Control: Enforcement Division Transfer, 1983. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Parole Board Report, 1987. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Department of Aviation: Aircraft Acquisition, 1986. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Department of Aviation: Aircraft Realignment, 1985. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Department of Aviation: Airport Approach Obstruction, 1986. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Department of Aviation: Metropolitan Washington Airports Transfer, 1984. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Department of Aviation: Metropolitan Washington Airports Transfer, 1984. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Department of Aviation: Metropolitan Washington Airports Transfer, 1984. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Department of Aviation: Dulles - Holton Commission, 1984-1986. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Department of Aviation: Dulles - Task Force, 1984-1985. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Department of Aviation: Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority, 1983-1988. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Department of Fire Programs: Arson Task Force, 1989. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Department of Fire Programs: Fire Programs Fund, 1986. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Staff Report on Alcohol Beverage Control Issues, 1987. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Department of Corresctions: Proposal to Replace State Pennitentiary, 1986. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles: Dealer Licensing Act, 1986. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Department of Transportation: Minutes, 1987. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Department of Transportation: Local Financing Subcommittee - Document 10, 1987. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Department of Transportation: Local Financing Subcommittee - Document 9, 1987. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Department of Transportation Report: Raising Speed Limit on Rural Interstates, 1987. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Department of Administration: National Air and Space Museum - Dulles Wing Phase 1, 1985. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Department of Administration: Washington Dulles International Airport Background Paper - Air Transportation Study, 1986. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Department of Transportation: Governor's Council on Transportation, 1977. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Department of Military Affairs: Study of State Responsibility for National Guard, 1986. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Governor's Office, 1986 Jan - 1986 Nov 12. (Box 4)
  - Governor's Office, 1986 Nov 13 - 1987 June 4. (Box 5)
  - Governor's Office, 1987 June 8- 1987 Nov. (Box 6)
  - Governor's Office, 1987 Dec - 1988 June. (Box 7)
  - Governor's Office, 1988 June - 1988 Dec. (Box 8)
  - Department of Transportation: Utterback Store Road, 1986. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Department of Transportation: Bristol Bypass, 1986. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Department of Transportation: Route 29 Bypass, 1989. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Department of Transportation: I-66 Widening, 1989. (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
  - Department of Transportation: Route 288, 1988. (Box 9, Folder 6-7)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles: Motorcycle Awareness, 1989. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Department of Transportation: York River Crossing, 1988. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Department of Transportation: Route 1 and 17 Connector, 1988. (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Department of Transportation: Van Dorn Village, 1989. (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Department of Transportation: Courthouse/Providence Roads Intersection, 1986. (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Department of Transportation: George P. Coleman Bridge, 1989. (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Department of Transportation: Culpeper Correctional Unit, 1989. (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Department of Transportation: Charles City County Prision Site, 1987. (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Department of Transportation: Tazewell County Prision Site, 1987. (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Department of Transportation: Ridgefield Road, 1989. (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Department of Transportation/Department of Correction: Muder by Inmate Mu'Min on Work Release, 1989. (Box 9, Folder 18-19)